בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is יא, Yud Aleph, and
we are in the... the גמרא Gemara is in the middle of
discussing
this position about... about whether a woman who is the wife of
a כהן, kohen, whether in principle she eats תרומה terumah from the
time of אירוסין erusin or from the time of נישואין. nisuin. The
גמרא Gemara got on this discussion from the question about its going
through the different ways in which a woman קידושין kiddushin is effected.
So we had כסף kesef and שטר shtar and then we're doing
ביאה. biah. And the question was whether ביאה biah creates קידושין kiddushin
or since ultimately the second stage נישואין nisuin is when they actualize
their marriage and start living together as husband and wife and... sex
is נישואין nisuin can be through חופה, chuppah, but it's also most...
in its most basic form done through them having sex in the
context of a married couple. The גמרא Gemara asks the question whether
when קידושין kiddushin is done through sex, whether that automatically just goes
straight to נישואין nisuin or not. And as a result of that
question, it was looking at the issue about the wife of a
כהן kohen who eats תרומה terumah and got into this discussion about
whether that starts from the time of אירוסין, erusin, from the time
of קידושין, kiddushin, or from the time of נישואין, nisuin, whether what
it is biblically. So really there are two models there. One could
debate this as what seemed to be from the ברייתא Braita the
גמרא Gemara quoting by יוחנן בן בג בג Yochanan ben Bag Bag
is that there was an actual debate whether biblically this starts at
which stage this starts. The argument that biblically it starts at the
stage of נישואין nisuin is based on the idea of כל טהור
בביתך יאכל קודש. kol tahor beveitcha yochal kodesh. Everybody pure in your
household. So the woman only comes into the man's house and is
part of the household, right, at the time of נישואין. nisuin. That's
the whole idea of נישואין. nisuin. She leaves her father's house and
she enters into the man's house. So that would be biblically from
the time of נישואין. nisuin. Whereas the other model would be like
the way a slave eats תרומה, terumah, and that's because of קנין
כספו, kinyan kaspo, the things that I own and have purchased, which
again evokes that whole idea of קידושין kiddushin as a type of
a purchase. And if that were true, it would be from the
time of קידושין. kiddushin. So that's a way of seeing this as
a debate whether biblically it's of the time of קידושין kiddushin or
נישואין. nisuin. And actually it seems to have been a debate of
תנאים. Tannaim. In the end, the בבלי Bavli decides that according to
everybody it's from the time of קידושין, kiddushin, and the only question
is whether what reason rabbinically did we push it off to the
time of נישואין? nisuin? Interestingly though, the
ירושלמי Yerushalmi really embraces the approach that even biblically it's from the
time of נישואין nisuin and it's based on this idea of כל
טהור בביתך. kol tahor beveitcha. So again, that's really interesting. It's interesting
in terms of the question of תרומה, terumah, but of course it's
also interesting from the perspective of what is קידושין, kiddushin, what is
נישואין, nisuin, to what degree is קידושין kiddushin a type of a
קניין kinyan and then נישואין nisuin is really the sense about being
a member of the household. Anyway, so that's where the גמרא Gemara
left off. That there was a debate about... so let's pick up
at the bottom of י עמוד ב Yud Amud Bet with that
in mind.
Yes? Were you... were you saying that the conclusion was that if
there's sex at קידושין kiddushin it automatically becomes נישואין? nisuin?
No,
the גמרא Gemara did not resolve that question. The גמרא Gemara did
not resolve that question. Okay? So let's actually pick up just to
get our... just to get our context from about eight lines, ten
lines from the bottom of י עמוד ב. Yud Amud Bet. רבינא
אמר, Ravina amar, the line starts with the word אמר, amar, maybe
it's 12 lines from the bottom. מדאורייתא מיפשט פשיטא ליה דאכלה. de-oraisa
mipsha peshita lei de-achla. Everybody agrees that this debate of the תנאים
Tannaim that really biblically she eats תרומה terumah from the time of
קידושין, kiddushin, although it does sound like that's actually what they were
debating. But anyway,
ומדרבנן הוא דשלח ליה. u-miderabbanan hu deshalach lei. And actually the message
that... who was it that יוחנן בן בג בג Yochanan ben Bag
Bag sent to רבי יהודה בן בתירה Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira was
a discussion of what the rabbinic issue is. ומדרבנן הוא דשלח ליה.
u-miderabbanan hu deshalach lei. והכי שלח ליה. v'hachi shalach lei. Here's what
he sent to him. שמעתי עליך שאתה אומר ארוסה בת ישראל לא
אכלה בתרומה. shamati alecha she-atah omer arusah bat Yisrael lo achlah biterumah.
I heard that you said
that... biblically speaking eats תרומה... terumah... ולא חיישת לסמפון. lo chayashta lesimpon.
And you're not concerned for סמפון. simpon. סמפון simpon is some type
of a defect that's going to be discovered... after they get to
נישואין. nisuin. So if at the time of נישואין, nisuin, after they
get married and they become intimate, he realizes like, oh she had
some, I don't know, some type of a... of a mark on
her body or whatever, some type of a thing that he's decided
is a substantive defect and therefore the קידושין kiddushin is going to
be בטל batel because he'll only discover that later at the time
of נישואין. nisuin. Then it'll turn out that retroactively the קידושין kiddushin
had never been good and she was eating
תרומה terumah inappropriately. So that would be the reason to wait for
נישואין, nisuin, because you don't want there to be a defect discovered
at נישואין nisuin and then retroactively her... never to have been a
good קידושין. kiddushin. So I heard that that's that you said that
in principle she could eat from the time of אירוסין erusin and
you're not concerned about discovering a defect. שלח ליה. Shalach lei. He
sent back to him, אתה אומר כן? atah omer ken? Don't you
agree? מוחזני בך שאתה בקי בחדרי תורה לדרוש בקל וחומר. muchzani bach
she-atah baki bechadrei torah lidrosh be-kal vachomer. I have a tradition about
you that you are an expert in the inner chambers of the
Torah to expound via קל וחומר. kal vachomer. אי אתה יודע, iy
attah yode'a, you know about קל וחומרים, kal vakhomers, don't you know
ומה שפחה כנענית שביאתה מאכילתה בתרומה כספה מאכילתה בתרומה? u-mah shifkhah kena'anis
she-bi'atah makhilasah bi-trumah kaspah makhilasah bi-trumah?
By a non-Jewish slave, you know, having sex with her does not
allow her to eat תרומה. trumah. It's not about being, you know,
it's not—that's not the act that makes her the slave, and that's
not relevant. What's relevant is that she's been purchased, okay, and she
eats תרומה. trumah. Now, how is this relevant for a דרבנן derabbanan
discussion? ולא חיישינן לסימפון, ve-lo khashinan le-simpon, and we're not afraid that
after he purchased her sometime down the road, he'll find some defect.
So if we're not concerned rabbinically by a slave that she can
eat תרומה trumah and about finding a defect, זו שביאתה מאכילתה בתרומה
אינו דין שכספה מאכילתה בתרומה ולא נחוש לסימפון? zu she-bi'atah makhilasah bi-trumah
eino din she-kaspah makhilasah bi-trumah ve-lo nekhush le-simpon? It's a strange קל
וחומר kal vakhomer now because we're dealing with a rabbinic point. But
anyways, this one that she—that there's more ways of making her your
wife, it could be through ביאה, bi'ah, it could be through כסף.
kesef. Anyway, the basic argument is, again, it's weak because this קל
וחומר kal vakhomer isn't so relevant—we're talking about a rabbinic point. But
the point is, if we're not afraid of finding a defect by
the case of this slave, why are we afraid by the case
of the wife? אבל, aval, so in principle, I really am not
concerned about this defect, okay? But in practice, I agree that a
woman cannot eat תרומה trumah from the time of אירוסין. eirusin. Why?
Not because of this concern about defect, but אבל מה אעשה שהרי
אמרו חכמים ארוסה בת ישראל אינה אוכלת בתרומה, aval mah e'eseh she-harei
amru khakhamim arusah bas yisrael einah okheles bi-trumah, that an ארוסה arusah
cannot eat תרומה trumah עד שתכנס לחופה, ad she-tikanes le-khuppah, until חופה.
khuppah. Why? משום דעולא. mishum de-Ula. Now
obviously those are not the words of the תנא tanna because עולא
Ula came much later, but anyway, and for dozen reasons, not for
the reason of defect, but for the reason of עולא. Ula. What's
עולא's Ula reason? Is that if you feed your wife who you're
betrothed, your ארוסה, arusah, תרומה, trumah, and she's not yet living in
your house, you're going to send her some תרומה trumah to where
she's living in her father's house, and she's going to have her
father and her brothers share in the תרומה. trumah. So that's why.
So in the end, what the גמרא gemara is framing is as
opposed to the simple read of this debate, which is that there
was a real debate whether biblically a woman who's an ארוסה arusah
to a כהן kohen eats תרומה trumah or not. Is it based
on the idea of קנין כספו kinyan kaspo and then she would
eat from the time of אירוסין, eirusin, or is it based on
the idea of ביתך beisecha and she would only eat from the
time of נישואין? nisu'in? The גמרא gemara now is saying that according
to everybody, she biblically eats from the time of אירוסין. eirusin. The
debate is what is the reason the rabbis told her she had
to wait till the time of נישואין. nisu'in. One explanation is a
concern that at נישואין nisu'in a defect—he'll decide that, oh, that wasn't
the woman I was expecting, and therefore retroactively will never have been
good the קידושין kiddushin and she'll have been eating תרומה trumah and
never have been married. And the other concern is that if she's
eating as an ארוסה arusah while she's not yet living with him,
she'll have her brother and her father's share in it, and they
will violate. So now the גמרא gemara says, what difference does it—well,
let's first finish this first. We're going to figure out, a, why
not to be concerned about a defect, what the difference is about
defect concern, why it would be a different concern rather than a
defect concern, and the other would be an issue of, or whatever,
why to be concerned about a defect here more than by slaves.
And the other is, as long as she's not eating תרומה, trumah,
what difference does it make what the reason is if everybody agrees
she doesn't eat תרומה trumah until נישואין. nisu'in. So the גמרא gemara
says like
this, they find out after נישואין nisu'in anyway, so even נישואין nisu'in
could be mistaken.
Well, but at a certain point you, you know, you no longer
have an opportunity, like you know you can, you know you have
a thirty days, you know you can return the object within thirty
days afterwards, we assume that you had a chance to get some,
you know, whatever to see it and you were מוחל. mokhel.
Yeah, well, and this קל וחומר, kal vakhomer, they go from ביאה
bi'ah to כסף, kesef, should be the other way around. I don't
understand that קל וחומר. kal vakhomer.
What do you mean?
If, if by an
אשה ishah ביאה bi'ah works to make her your wife and it
doesn't work by a slave, and so to make her your slave,
and by, so therefore כסף kesef which works—which does work certainly, basically
the category of wife she should be more entitled to תרומה trumah
than a slave because there's easier ways she could become your wife
than somebody could become your slave, more ways. So the גמרא gemara
says like this, ובין בן בגבג סימפון בעבדים לית ליה. u-ven ban
bagbag simpon be-avadim leis lei.
One minute. So what is the explanation? Why does בן בגבג Ben
Bagbag think there's a concern of סימפון simpon of a defect by
the case of the wife? That's his explanation why she doesn't eat
תרומה, trumah, because of a concern that a defect will be discovered.
But why is that any different than the case of slaves where
we're not concerned about that and we let slaves eat תרומה trumah
right away? So the גמרא gemara says, well, here's the reason. Because
by slaves, אי ממה שבגלוי הא קחזי ליה, i mi-mah she-bi-galui ha
kakhazi lei, if it was something that was visible, he could have
seen it. What is there left to discover by a slave, right?
You go to the slave market, you look at your slave, what
defect is there that you're not seeing? You know, it's like buyer
beware. If there were something to, you know, if you didn't check
it out at the time and it was able to be checked
out, so anything that could have been seen, you saw, and either
you—either you didn't see and you were מוחל mokhel because you were
irresponsible because it's your obligation to check, or you saw and you
were okay with it. So אי ממה שבגלוי הא קחזי ליה, i
mi-mah she-bi-galui ha kakhazi lei, you see it. אי משום מום שבסתר,
i mishum mum she-bi-seser, let's say that there's something that's, I don't
know, some type of a deformity or something that's hidden from you
that's like, you know, that's— under her clothes or his clothes or
whatever by the slave. So מאי נפקא מינה? mai nafka mina? So
what difference does that make? במלאכה קבעי ליה, bemlacha kabaie leh, that
doesn't affect why you're buying a slave; you're not buying a slave
for appearance purposes, okay, so that can't be a claim that that
was some substantive
defect, okay, presumably in contrast to the wife, you know, the question,
the issue is that that again, I, you know, you can't escape
the obvious sort of purchase model here that's being used and the
whole idea about a defect and so on and also whatever, it's
more than just the act of קידושין kiddushin as purchase, it's treating
it as a defect and a מקח טעות, mekach ta'os, you know,
there's a certain commodification here that obviously is just, you know, is
very disturbing, but the idea would be that, you know, well once
you know they're intimate and she's naked, he decides that there's something
about her body he doesn't like, that's okay, that's by a wife,
that's irrelevant by the slave. So לא איכפת ליה. lo ichpas leh.
Now, how about if there's something you can't see that's not physical?
You checked them out at the time, but you didn't realize other
aspects about him that you couldn't check out at the time. נמצא
גנב או קוביוסטוס, nimtza gannav o kubyustos,
if he was turned out that he was a גנב gannav or
קוביוסטוס, kubyustos, which Rashi says means a kidnapper, but I'll talk in
a minute about what Tosafot says that means. הגיעו, hige'o, you know
what? You got what you deserved because you know, that's what slaves
are, you should have expected that. You can't complain about that, that's
to be expected, okay? Again, like...
yeah,
yeah, you know, whatever, I mean this obviously... what? Yeah, presumably not
on robbery. גנב gannav is right. That well that's the next question
the Gemara's going to ask. מאי אמרת? mai amart? לסטים מזויין? listis
mezuyan? Maybe you're afraid that he'll be an armed robber, some real
type of a, you know, thing that's really terrible that you don't
normally you don't expect by slaves? או נכתב למלכות? o nichtav lemalchus?
Or maybe the king has, you know, he's been, you know, he's
been signed over to the king, meaning that there's some type of
a, you know, of a that he's going to be executed by
the government. So if that's true and you didn't know where that
that sentence was passed, so הנהו קלא אית להו, hanu kala ishu
lehu, those would have been you would have known about it. Okay,
so now Rashi says what it means that קלא אית להו kala
ishu lehu means if that were true, then you knew about it
and you were okay with it. Tosafot says, no, no, no. If
those, we're assuming that because they would be easily known, that you
cannot that therefore like we're not in general going to be concerned
about a סימפון, simpon, because we're going to assume that that'll never
be the case, because somebody will know about it and won't buy
it under those circumstances. If it turned out that it was true
and somehow it was not known, maybe that would be a basis
for being מבטל, mevatel, but we're going to let a slave eat
תרומה terumah and we're not going to be concerned about this type
of a scenario because if that that was the scenario, he would
have known about it and never purchased the slave to begin with.
Okay, so therefore by slave, now of course I don't know, let's
say you find you get him home and you find out that
he's got a bad personality and that he's very, you know, and
he's disrespectful and he refuses to listen to you or whatever. So
I don't know exactly. But okay, anyway the Gemara says that there's
more of a concern of סימפון, simpon, of finding something that would
make it a קידושי טעות kiddushei ta'us by the case by the
woman than there is by the case by the slave and therefore
they didn't want the woman to eat תרומה terumah until after the
נישואין. nissu'in. I do want to say, you know, it's also very
disturbing in addition to the I mean what's disturbing, look, besides the
sort of, you know, commodification as it were, or, you know, treating
them like the property, is that it's not parallel, and not only
is it not parallel, not only as a point of principle but
as a practice in terms of the issues of like עגונה. agunah.
You know, sometimes a basis of being מבטל mevatel a קידושין kiddushin
in the case of an עגונה agunah is to say that it
was a קידושי טעות. kiddushei ta'os. That it turned out that the
guy was a pathological liar or, you know, other terrible things, right?
And that therefore nobody would have wanted to marry him, she never
would have wanted to marry him had she known that. And so
that's, you know, very reasonable to say that any normal person had
they known that would not have married them. And there's a very
strong resistance amongst, you know, the vast, you know, certainly contemporary פוסקים,
poskim, you know, to allow to acknowledge a קידושי טעות kiddushei ta'os
in those circumstances. Whereas when it comes for the fact that if
there was a problem with the woman, right, then the Gemara seems
much more, you know, ready to acknowledge that. You know, and that
does come again from this model: there's a purchaser and an object
being purchased, right? So, you know, it's you could say it's based
on the Gemara טב למיתב טן דו, tav lemeitav tan du, women
are more okay with like any type of a guy, but it
also has to do with who's the purchaser and who's the one
being purchased. You know, and if that's your basic model, then a
defect in the woman is a, you know, in the Gemara, appears
as a much more ready basis for ביטול קידושין bitul kiddushin than
a defect in the man, and that really plays out sadly in
cases of עגונה. agunah. One more point is Tosafot קוביוסטוס, kubyustos, the
acute Tosafot about what's what's קוביוסטוס. kubyustos. So he says he quotes
an interesting Gemara, he
says פירוש הקונטרס גונב נפשות קשה דפרק קמא דבכורות, perush hakuntres gonev
nefashot kasha deperek kama debichoros, אמר אשל קונטריקוס, amar ashal kuntrikos, almost
sounds like
קוביוסטוס, kubyustos, anyway somebody הקצר לרבי יוחנן בן זכאי גבי שקלים ובקע
לגלגולת בגבוי הכסף, hakatzar l'rabbi yochanan ben zakkai gabai shekalim u'veka l'gulgoles
bigivoi hakesef, okay when they got a, you know, a בקע beka
a half of a shekel for each
person. Okay, anyway, so he says if you do the math in
the תורה, Torah, it doesn't add up based on the number of
people and the amount it says they collected at the end and
the half of the שקל, shekel, and he said to him, you
know, the math in the תורה Torah doesn't add up. This is
what this non-Jew asked רבי יוחנן בן זכאי Rebbi Yochanan ben Zakkai
and he said to him, משה רבכם, Moshe Rabbachem, so it must
be משה, Moshe, your teacher, גנב היה, ganav haya, either was a
thief and he pocketed the difference and he only wrote, you know,
the amount left over in the
תורה, Torah, או קוביוסטוס היה, o kubyostos haya, or he was a
קוביוסטוס, kubyostos, או אינו בקי בחשבונות, o eino baki b'cheshbonos, or he
was bad at math.
So, what's the explanation? So, okay, anyway, obviously a very disrespectful way
of asking the question, but you see that קוביוסטוס kubyostos does not
mean a, you know, a kidnapper. ומה ענין גונב נפשות לחסרון שקלים?
U'ma inyan goneiv nefashos l'chisaron shekalim? וכן פירש ר"ח דקוביוסטוס משחק בקוביא,
V'chein pirush Rabbeinu Chananel d'kubyostos mesacheik b'kubia, a gambler. So, why, why
was the numbers wrong? It must be he was a gambler and
he had to spend all the money to pay off his gambling
debts. And so you only left the balance, you know. So that
makes sense, you know, how we suspect, yeah, normal slaves is going
to be a thief or a gambler. You know, this attitude, you
know, about, you know, assuming that the, you know, that slaves were
of low morals was obviously very, very widespread. Okay. ועדא דאמר בבראשית
רבה, V'hada d'amar b'Bereishis Rabbah, ויאמר שלחני כי עלה השחר, Vayomer shalcheini
ki ala hashachar, right by יעקב Yaakov and the angel. דקאמר ליה
יעקב למלאך וכי גנב את? או קוביוסטוס את? D'ka-amar lei Yaakov l'malach
v'chi ganav ata? O kubyostos ata? Why do you have to go?
Because it's morning? Are you a thief or a קוביוסטוס, kubyostos, שאתה
מתיירא מן השחר? she'ata misyarei min hashachar? So לפירוש הקונטרס ניחא, l'peirush
hakuntres nicha, because, you know, he's a what do you call it,
he's a kidnapper. ולפירוש רבינו חננאל נמי אית למימר דאדם שמשחק בקוביא
רבים היו עליו נושים הרבה ונחבא בפניהם. U'l'pirush Rabbeinu Chananel nami is
l'meimar d'adam she'mesacheik b'kubia rabbim hayu alav noshim harbei v'nichba bifneihem. Yeah,
he's got a lot of debt, creditors, so yeah, he goes into
hiding at daytime. You know, he has to stay out of people's
eyes because he's deeply in debt. So, I thought that that was
a nice little, good read of the word קוביוסטוס. kubyostos. Yeah, you
had a question?
Is there anything about how קידושי ביאה kiddushei bia works insofar as,
meaning there's a שטר shtar that says הרי את מקודשת לי? harei
at mekudeshes li? Right. בביאה, b'bia, do they say anything, like, you
know, הרי את מקודשת לי בביאה זו? harei at mekudeshes li b'bia
zu? Like, yeah.
So, right,
because, you know, then obviously a man and a woman is let's
say people just living together but they're not saying anything.
So that's a very good question. I mean, so I believe actually
in the תוספתא Tosefta it says that, if memory serves. The base
question that you're asking, you know what, let me read two more
sentences and finish up this issue about the, about the what do
you call it, about the תרומה terumah and then I'll answer your
question. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. מכדי, בין למר
בין למר לא אכלה. Michdi, bein l'mar bein l'mar lo achla.
Whether the reason is because of סמפון simpon that and therefore retroactively
the קידושין kiddushin will be בטל, batel, or the reason is is
because she might feed her brothers the תרומה terumah while she's in
her father's house. Either way, she doesn't eat it as an ארוסה.
arusa. מאי בינייהו? Mai beinaihu? What difference does it make which reason
you give? So the גמרא Gemara says, איכא בינייהו קיבל או מסר
והלך. Ika beinaihu kibeil o masar v'halach.
Or you could read that it's three things. So קיבל kibeil means
that the guy said, you know what, I am accepting to marry
her regardless of anything I find out afterwards. He says that from
the outset. So in that case, he basically, you know, waives any
rights to sort of say that it was a, you know, thank
you, that it was a, that there was a some defect or
something, and therefore she could eat תרומה terumah right away if that's
the reason, if the reason is סמפון. simpon. Now, מסר והלך masar
v'halach is the scenarios where the father gives the girl over to
the agents of the husband, but the husband isn't there yet. He's
still back in his home and she's traveling, you know, from New
York to Miami, but she's with the agents from the husband. So
in that case,
there's still a concern of סמפון, simpon, right, because he has not
yet been intimate with her. מומין, mumin, right, that's what סמפון simpon
is. But there's no concern that she'll feed her, her family because
she's now no longer with her family. So in that case, that
would be the flip. So that would be some נפקא מינה. nafka
mina. Now, so that's the end of that discussion. Now, Michael asks
an excellent question about to what degree is קידושי ביאה kiddushei bia
like everything else. Like by קידושי ביאה, kiddushei bia, does it have
to first of all be before עדים? eidim? So the answer is
yes, although it's very awkward. Because actually in an earlier, in his
first פירוש המשניות Pirush HaMishnayos on the משנה Mishnah of קידושין Kiddushin
of בכסף בשטר ובביאה, b'chesef b'shtar u'b'bia, the רמב"ם Rambam said that
they have to actually have sex in the presence of עדים. eidim.
Later he amended that to say that it means that they have
to be in private in the presence of עדים eidim with a
presumption that they're having
sex. Like עדי ייחוד עדי ביאה. edei yichud edei bia. Right, עדי
ייחוד עדי ביאה. edei yichud edei bia. Now how about does he
have to
say הרי את מקודשת לי בביאה זו? harei at mekudeshes li b'bia
zu? So I think that's in the תוספתא. Tosefta. I think the
תוספתא Tosefta says. ובביאה, U'b'bia, no, actually no, actually I remembered it
was תוספתא, Tosefta, but תוספתא Tosefta actually says a different point. Listen
to the תוספתא. Tosefta. It says בכסף, נתן לה כסף או שוה
כסף, הרי את מקודשת לי הרי את מאורסת לי. B'chesef, nasan la
kesef o shaveh kesef, harei at mekudeshes li, harei at me'oreses li.
ובשטר, בשטר. U'b'shtar, b'shtar. So it says הרי את, אפילו כתב על
החרס ועל הנייר הרי זה מקודשת. harei at, afilu kasav al hacheres
v'al haniyar, harei zu mekudeshes. Now, ובביאה, כל ביאה שהיא לשם קידושין
מקודשת, שאינה לשם קידושין אינה מקודשת. u'b'bia, kol bia she'hi l'shem kiddushin
mekudeshes, she'eina l'shem kiddushin eina mekudeshes. So the תוספתא Tosefta does not
say that you say a formal statement of הרי את. harei at.
It doesn't say what is the context? Is it done in the
context of קידושין kidushin? *kiddushin* or not in the context. Now and
that points to the idea that ביאה *bi'ah* might not be the
same type of a formal act. Like this is a formal act.
ביאה *bi'ah* might be to use like more that it's a מציאות
*metziyus*. The lived reality of them not just having sex because you
can have sex in a non-marital context, but the lived reality of
having sex in a marriage context that it's לשם קידושין kiddushin. *lesheim
kiddushin*, right, that that creates the reality of marriage. It's sort of
like a, you know, like common law marriage or not you know
a de facto marriage. If they are basically being having sex together
in the context of a married couple then they're then they're married.
It's not because the act is like an act that effects the
marriage as much as it's the reality that's being created that effects
the marriage. Now the big נפקא מינא nafka mina *nafka mina* of
this so okay there's a technical question, right, how much is the
עדים edim, *edim* playing the same type of a role do you
even need עדים *edim* although presumably apparently you do. Do you need
it to be הרי את מקודשת *harei at mekudeshet* or does it
just have to be לשם *lesheim* does it just have to frame
the context? Right I think the תוספתא *Tosefta* is very clear to
distinguish between הרי את מקודשת *harei at mekudeshet* as opposed to לשם
קידושין kiddushin, *lesheim kiddushin*. But the big נפקא מינא nafka mina. *nafka
mina* is exactly the question of common law marriage. If people are
living together and never had a קידושין *kiddushin* and are just I
don't know secular marriage even and they're you know and having sex
as a married couple right and everybody knows about it so you
could sort like that they're living together as a married couple so
you could say that creates עדים *edim* it's just אנן סהדי *anan
sahedi* everybody's aware of that reality. So maybe they're halakhically married and
maybe the woman needs a גט *get* and maybe if if it's
so that is a big big debate. Rabbi יהודה הרצוג *Yehuda Hertzog*
Henkin basically paskened that even if you could be מבטל *mivatel* the
קידושין *kiddushin* because you could say there were פסול עדים *pasul edim*
or whatever you could say or you know basically that everybody who's
living together as husband and wife is קידושי ביאה *kiddushei bi'ah* and
and you need a גט *get*. Now that has huge consequences obviously.
So רב בני בנים *Rav Bnei Banim*?
Yeah. No, no, I said רב יהודה הרצוג *Rav Yehuda Hertzog* I'm
sorry, רב יוסף Rav Yosef אליהו *Rav Yosef Eliyahu* Henkin, excuse me,
the grandfather, the grandfather who was the preeminent פוסק *posek* in America
before רב משה *Rav Moshe*, yeah. And רב משה *Rav Moshe* strongly
disagreed and I mean you you know and that's how how you're
able to deal with cases where there was a קידושין *kiddushin* but
you know there's not a גט *get* like a like a lot
of cases רב משה *Rav Moshe* dealt with in terms of a
case of a conservative קידושין *kiddushin* where he was able to say
well there weren't kosher עדים *edim* or this or that and therefore
he
did not need to get out of the בית דין *beis din*.
What? רב משה *Rav Moshe* held that you don't say that the
ביאה *bi'ah* when it's not done as a מעשה ביאה לשם קידושין
*ma'aseh bi'ah lesheim kiddushin* that the act you have כוונה *kavannah* that
the particular act should effect קידושין *kiddushin* that it's like any other
act he feels it's like כסף kesef, *kesef* it's like שטר *shtar*
if you don't have כוונה *kavannah* that this act of sex should
effect קידושין *kiddushin* then there's no קידושין *kiddushin*. So because and therefore
it's not this מציאות *metziyus* of them living together as husband and
wife. It's a good לומדות *lomdus* but it's really bad הלכה halacha
*halakha*. I mean it's really like you know in terms of the
human implication I mean it's it's disaster.
Meaning they don't want to like be together then they're really
they never had an act that was a מעשה קידושין maaseh kiddushin,
*ma'aseh kiddushin* and that allowed him to basically say that and in
cases where there was not something that was done as an intentional
act of halakhic קידושין *kiddushin* that the woman doesn't need a גט
*get* and you know so that allowed him to deal with a
lot a lot of cases. So it's a huge נפקא מינא *nafka
mina*. So I'm glad that you raised that question. Okay, yes. Alright,
so let's move along. Yeah, yeah, it's also getting yeah yeah. Alright,
so it's we got a whole nice shadow thing going on in
the video here. What's it called? Chiaroscuro? What's the word? Light and
dark? Chiaroscuro.
Chiaroscuro. Okay anyway yeah you can watch the video afterwards and see
it's a very artistic rendering here. Special effects of the video, thank
you, that's great. כסף kesef, *kesef*. Now we doubled back to talking
about כסף kesef *kesef*. Okay, בכסף *be'kesef*. בית שמאי Beis Shammai's אומרים
דדינר *Beis Shammai omrim de'dinar*. So now here's the interesting question. If
it's כסף kesef *kesef* and it's purely symbolic, so בית הלל Beis
Hillel's *Beis Hillel* says it's a פרוטה prutah. *perutah* that's the penny
that's the smallest coin of the realm. Why does בית שמאי Beis
Shammai's *Beis Shammai* say a דינר dinar *dinar*? What's the logic for
that? Now what would be valuable here, valuable haha anyway, is to
talk about the relative coinage here about it. So I actually had
a chart here. Let me see if I still have it on
my thing. Yep, I do. Okay. פרוטה prutah, *perutah*,
איסר *issar*, פונדיון *pundion*,
מעה ma'ah *ma'ah*
or
גרה
*gerah*, 20 גרה השקל *gerah hashekel*. Okay. איסטירא
*istira* or sometimes called a טרפעיק *tarapic*. Okay, we're not going to
deal with all of these. דינר dinar, *dinar*, that's what בית שמאי
Beis Shammai *Beis Shammai* says, דינר dinar, *dinar*, which is also a
זוז zuz, *zuz* like the 200 זוז zuz, *zuz* of a כתובה
ksuva. *kesubah*. Okay.
תרי זוזי דפשא *trei zuzei de'pesha*.
שקל shekel *shekel*. Okay, and a סלע sela, *sela*. or a שקל
הקודש. shekel hakodesh, Okay, anyway, okay. Now here are, so in,
here's how much these are worth in פרוטות. prutos. Okay,
one, eight, sixteen, thirty-two,
ninety-six, I mean you can see obviously it's, you know, some type
of a function of two here, sixty-four, oh
that's
by three, that's true, that's true, okay, one hundred and
ninety-two. Okay, so by the way, just to stop here a moment
and to see that according to בית שמאי's Beit Shammai דינר dinar,
is almost two hundred times בית הלל's Beis Hillel. פרוטה. prutah, So
if this is a penny, this is about two dollars, just so
you have a rough sense about the difference. Okay, שקל shekel, is
double that, is three hundred and eighty-four, okay, but a סלע, sela
which is a שקל הקודש, shekel hakodesh, meaning when the תורה Torah
says שקל, shekel, is seven hundred and sixty-eight, which is four times
as much. So by the way, okay, this one דינר, dinar, not
four times, one דינר, dinar
no, no, no, I meant of a דינר, dinar, one דינר, dinar,
one זוז, zuz, right, so if this is one זוז, zuz a
סלע sela is four זוז, zuz. which is why when the תורה
Torah says that what you pay for the case of the seducer
or the rapist is fifty שקל, shekel okay, this is שקל shekel
הקודש,
fifty שקל shekel,
equals
the two hundred זוז zuz, of the כתובה. kesuvah.
Okay,
you see that? Yes? So בית שמאי's Beit Shammai דינר dinar, is
what's often called in rabbinic literature, it's often called a זוז. zuz.
Okay, maybe let's take this out because this is confusing because there
are two שקלים, shekels, but we'll take that out. Okay, the סלע
sela. or the שקל shekel, in the תורה Torah is four times
that amount. So when the תורה Torah says that a case of
the rapist or the seducer is fifty שקל, shekel that's מוהר הבתולות,
mohar habesulos, right, the מוהר, mohar, the bride price of virgins, so
if it's fifty שקל, shekel so a שקל shekel is four זוז,
zuz, it's two hundred זוז. zuz Yes, you got that? Okay, fine.
All right, anyway, so that's just because obviously that's very relevant in
terms of just, you know, the other part of אישות ishus is
that money, but in terms of what is the fifty שקל shekel
which is two hundred זוז, zuz but in terms of us, בית
שמאי Beit Shammai, is about two hundred times בית הלל. Beit Hillel,
Okay, so if this is a penny, this is about two dollars.
Yes, you should, no, you said the question why? Right? Think of
a number of reasons why. I mean, first of all, you know,
if you want this to be something that you're not just like
playing around and doing, you know, you've got to payoff.
I understand, but why this of all the possible coins that you
could pick, why pick this one? So let's take a look at
what the גמרא Gemara says. Okay, easy come, easy
go.
All right, let's take a look. גמרא Gemara says like this, בכסף
בית שמאי אומרים בדינר. Bekessef, Beis Shammai omrim bedinar. מאי טעמא דבית
שמאי? Mai tamai d'Beis Shammai? אמר רבי זעירא שכן אשה מקפדת על
עצמה ואין
מתקדשת בפחות מדינר. Amar Rabi Zeira, sheken isha makpedes al atzma v'ein
miskadeshes b'pachos midinar. Right? Like Michael said, you know, because if we
are, because I'm not going to agree to a
penny, so we assume that the standard minimum that a woman would
agree to would be this. Now the thing that sort of bothers
me is you could say oh that's very nice, it sort of
expresses the dignity, you know, a certain self-respect of the woman. On
the other hand, if you say it's a פרוטה, prutah. it's purely
symbolic, right? If you say, ah, I'm not going to do it
for anything less than ten dollars, so what is it? Is it
a real purchase? I mean, it's still symbolic, so you could say,
well, it's a, this is like a penny is like sort of
is an act of like, you know, like it's degrading, it's
insulting, so even if it is symbolic, there needs to be some
minimum, right, like say it's not the thought that, you know, it's
not the gift that, you know, it's whatever, it's not how much
it costs, it's the thought that counts, and then you give like
a little, I don't know, a plastic, you know, ring, it says
actually not a thought like this, you know, it's got to have
a little, so even if it's purely, so you could try to
say אשה מקפדת על עצמה isha makpedes al atzma with still within
symbolic and not saying it's purchase, but it's got to be something
that's not so trivial, you know, that speaks a little bit about
how much you care about me or how much, you know, says
something about how you value the marriage. So even if it's symbolic,
it can't be so trivial. It's got to be something of some
minimum value, some significant value. Okay? Yes.
So like under the חופה, chuppah, like when the עדים, right, right
before this, right, right before the מעשה קידושין, it is שוה פרוטה,
shaveh prutah, right, you've got this ring that's five
thousand dollars, not five thousand, how about a hundred dollars?
Okay, yes, whatever, a gold band. Right, okay, gold band, right, right,
hundred and fifty, right. So but like if it's a trivialization of
the תורה Torah that asks that question.
So the reason actually, so I don't know if Dan covered this,
the reason that we ask under the חופה, chuppah, do you see
that it's worth a פרוטה, prutah is because of the whole סוגיא
sugya
about שירים, shiyurayim, about whether it's צריך שומא. tzarich shuma. So we,
so as a way of saying, we're not, the guy isn't promising
any value other than
a
פרוטה. prutah, אלא מעתה, Ella ma'ata,
right, אלא מעתה, Ella ma'ata, yeah, but then רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam
says that's, you know, whatever. אלא מעתה, Ella ma'ata, I assume he
covered that. אלא מעתה, Ella ma'ata, says the גמרא, Gemara, if it's
really because of what we assume that a woman is going to
be מקפיד makpid on, בנתי דרבי ינאי, benosei deRabbi Yannai,
let's talk about the daughters of רבי ינאי, Rabbi Yannai, who was
a wealthy family, דקפדי אנפשייהו, dakapdi anafshaihu,
they would be very מקפיד, makpid, ולא מיקדשי בפחות מתיכופתא דדינרי, velat
mekadshe bephoches mi-tichrafta de-dinari, they would refuse to accept anything less than
a basket filled with gold coins. So הכא נמי hacha nami of
דינר, dinar, not one דינר, dinar, a basket of דינרי. dinars. So
הכא נמי דפשטה ידה וקיבלה חד זוזא מאחר, hacha nami de-pashta yada
ve-kibla chad zuza me-acher, הכא נמי דלא הוי קידושין? hacha nami delo
havei kidushin?
Would you say that if she accepted one זוז zuz from one
guy, notice a זוז zuz, is the same as a דינר, dinar,
it's all using דינר, dinar, normally you'd assume, oh, I'm so important,
you'd have to give me like, I don't know, a diamond ring
worth a hundred thousand dollars, but if למעשה, lema'isa, the guy gave
her a ring and it was only worth a דינר, dinar, you're
telling me it wouldn't be קידושין? So the question is if you're
going by הקפדה, hakpada, פשטה ידה
וקיבלה,
pashta
yada
ve-kibla, obviously she's not מקפיד. makpid.
So that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to answer, but the
real point, the גמרא Gemara says is if you're going about the
question about what a woman is מקפיד makpid on, the real point
is when we talk about a person is מקפיד, makpid, it suggests
a subjective standard. You're not... that's not an objective definition. A פרוטה
prutah. is an objective definition of money, minimum amount of money. Anything
else, it's like, oh, well, it would be insulting to me. So
that's not an objective standard. Different women have different definitions of what's
insulting to them. So are you going to have a different definition
for every person? So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. So
the גמרא Gemara says, אמר ליה, amar lei, so as Michael says,
פשטה ידה וקיבלה לא קאמינא. pashta yada ve-kibla lo kamina. No, no,
if she willingly accepted, then whatever she agrees to, which is here
an amazing point. What it's saying is even according to בית שמאי
Beit Shammai. that says a minimum is a דינר, dinar,
that's if she wasn't aware, and we'll get to how she wouldn't
be aware in a minute. But if she agrees to accept less
than a דינר, dinar? if she agrees to accept a פרוטה, prutah
that will work. Now, so then... no, because that's a definition of
money, that's not a הקפדה. hakpada. Okay, but you're right, it's all
about הקפדה, hakpada, and if she agrees to less than a דינר,
dinar? it will work. So then if she agrees to less than
a דינר, dinar. it will work, what's the case where it needs
to be a דינר? dinar? So the גמרא Gemara says, בכי קאמינא,
be-ki-kamina, what am I talking about? דקדשה בליליא, de-kadsha beleilya, it was
nighttime and she couldn't count the money, אי נמי דשוויא שליח, i
nami de-shavsha shaliach, or she had made an agent to it. So
therefore, in a case where she doesn't know what was given, that's
where we're going to sort of take a standard, and as far
as... and I told you sort of insert this, it's not exactly
clear how the גמרא Gemara is answering this, and as far as
your question that if it's subjective, every person should be different, you
know, it's a type of a, you know, it's a type of
a, you go כדרך בני אדם, ke-derech benei adam, right, you go
by, you go by a universal standard. It is based on הקפדה,
hakpada, on personal הקפדה, hakpada, but it's a presumed minimum הקפדה hakpada
that everybody has. So if a person actively, consciously accepts less, it'll
work, a פרוטה. prutah When does בית שמאי Beit Shammai say a
דינר? dinar. When she's not aware what she's accepting, and then we're
going to presume a minimum הקפדה hakpada of a דינר. dinar Okay,
so that's an answer which is okay, but it's not deeply satisfying,
right? Ultimately, it's rooted in the person's psychology, not in some type
of a definition. So the גמרא Gemara says, רב יוסף אמר, Rav
Yosef amar, so רב יוסף gives a different reason. טעמא דבית שמאי,
ta'ama de-Beit Shammai, כדרב יהודה, ki-de-Rav Yehuda, אמר רב, amar Rav, אמר
רב אסי, amar Rav Assi, דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב אסי, damar
Rav Yehuda amar Rav Assi, כל כסף האמור בתורה, kol kesef ha-amur
ba-Torah, כסף צורי, kesef Tzuri, ושל דבריהם, כסף מדינה. veshel divreihem kesef
medinah. So now... what? Tyrian? Oh, yeah. So now, okay, this is
going to get a little complicated, but anyway, whenever the תורה Torah
talks about כסף, kesef, okay, it's talking about, it's talking about this
Tyrian, צורי Tzuri type of money, which is basically of silver, whereas
when the Rabbis say that something is going to cost X amount
of שקל shekel, or something of that nature, they're talking about the
standard local coinage, and the let me just... כסף מדינה. kesef Medina.
Now, the basic point is, it's a little confusing because the point
is that you can use the same words, like if you say
a dollar, right, are we talking about Canadian dollars, US dollars, Australian
dollars? Now, there's not a big variance there, right? But the difference
between talking about the same word for the coinage, if you're talking
about כסף צורי kesef Tzuri and כסף מדינה, kesef Medina. is a
one to eight ratio. So it's huge, okay? And therefore, by the
way, we, you know, in כתובות, Ketuvos, which is not what we're
learning now, the question is is כתובה דאורייתא Ketuvah de-Oraisah or דרבנן,
de-Rabbanan, and if you figure out the fifty שקל shekel or two
hundred זוז zuz. and in their דאורייתא de-Oraisah amount or in their
כסף מדינה kesef Medina, amount, which would be one-eighth of their דאורייתא
de-Oraisah amount. So it's a big difference whether we assume we're talking
about a Rabbinic obligation and the coinage therefore is coinage that's worth
one-eighth of what the same coinage would be of the same... you
know, there's two coinage systems, right? There's צורי, Tzuri, if you want
to call it like the royal coinage, and the local coinage, and
they all... and the coins have the same names, but the local
coinage is one-eighth. of a value of the royal coinage. Now, how
is any of that relevant to us? It's only relevant to us
because what it's basically saying is, is that since the תורה Torah
says, this is what we're going to get to say, קיחה-קיחה, kicha
kicha, right? There's a woman is כי יקח ki yikach and we
learn it from שדה עפרון Sdeh Ephron and there it says נתתי
כסף השדה, natati kesef hasadeh, כסף, kesef right? So that's a כסף
kesef. that's written in the תורה. Torah. So the smallest silver coin,
this is a copper coin, like a penny. Okay? The smallest silver
coin is, now here's a little bit of a question, is the
smallest silver coin a מעה ma'ah. or is it a דינר? dinar.
It's not exactly clear. The גמרא Gemara is going to be a
little confused about that, but it seems like the smallest silver coin
is a מעה. ma'ah? So therefore, even if you say look, it's
a כסף kesef written in the תורה, Torah, it has to be
a silver coin, it doesn't explain why we're getting to a דינר.
dinar, Why don't we just stop at a מעה? ma'ah. So רש"י,
Rashi, רש"י Rashi grapples with this and רש"י Rashi says, well, once
it's not a copper coin isn't going to be enough, we're going
to have to assume it's going to have to be something of
significant, so it's going to be this level of a silver coin.
תוספות Tosafot says I don't understand, if the only coinage the תורה
Torah refers to is silver coinage, it's not like it's dismissing this,
it's not even talking about this. And if it says כסף, kesef
right, it should be a מעה. ma'ah So that leads תוספות Tosafot
to say that actually the דינר dinar, is the smallest silver coin
in the תורה. Torah. Okay, but it doesn't really work with others
because we actually know that a מעה ma'ah, actually is כסף kesef.
and is smaller. Okay, so it's still not 100% clear, but the
basic point is the תורה Torah is talking, the coinage in the
תורה Torah is silver coinage, so a פרוטה prutah, is out. A
פרוטה prutah, is copper and therefore we're going to be talking about
a דינר. dinar All right, that's the basic answer. Now, we're going
to elaborate on this a bit. So let's take a look. גופא,
Gufa, let's look at that statement. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב כל
כסף האמור בתורה כסף צורי ובדבריהם כסף מדינה. Amar Rav Yehuda amar
Rav, kol kesef ha'amur baTorah kesef Tzuri u'vedivrehem kesef medinah. כללו, Klalo,
is this really a rule? והרי תנא, Ve'harei tanna, how about when
somebody makes a claim, right? This is מודה במקצת. modeh b'miktzat. You
know, I say, "Michael, you owe me $100," and you say, "No,
I only owe you 50," and you make a שבועה. shvuah. So
let's learn from the תורה Torah by it says כי יתן איש
אל רעהו כסף או כלים לשמור, Ki yiten ish el re'ehu kesef
o kelim lishmor, right? Somebody gives to his friend, you know, vessels
or money or vessels to watch. And later in that פרשה parsha
it says כי הוא זה, Ki hu zeh, "No, this is the
one," which חז"ל Chazal mean to say, "This is what I owe
you. I only owe you half, I don't owe you the other
half." And then it says you take a שבועה. shvuah. Okay, in
the simple sense of the תורה, Torah, we're talking about a שבועה
shvuah that a שומר shomer makes, but the way חז"ל Chazal understand
it, we're also talking about a שבועה shvuah of מודה במקצת. modeh
b'miktzat. Now, what size claim do I have to make and what
size admission do you have to make? So it says
ותנן, u't'nan, taught in the משנה, Mishna, שבועת הדיינים, shvuat haDayanim, when
you make this שבועה shvuah the judges impose this שבועה, shvuah, הטענה
שתי כסף, hata'ana shtei kesef, the claim has to be two כסף.
kesef. Now כסף kesef here means a מעה, ma'ah. okay, which is
really the smallest כסף kesef, coinage. Okay, it has to be two
כסף.
kesef Right, because otherwise I can't say the half of it, but
the smallest silver coin...
Right, but no, but והודאה, ve'hoda'ah,
one minute, but your concession שוה פרוטה. shaveh prutah. If you just
admit to owing me a פרוטה, prutah. why? Because the תורה Torah
says I gave you כסף. kesef? So I gave you, we'll see
in a minute why it's two, but I gave you this is
the smallest silver coin. Okay, here's where כסף kesef, thing comes in.
Okay, and this is copper, נחושת. nechoshet. Okay. So I gave you
the smallest silver coin and we'll see in a minute why it's
two, and that's כי יתן איש אל רעהו כסף. ki yiten ish
el re'ehu kesef. Now you say כי הוא זה, ki hu zeh,
כי הוא זה ki hu zeh means you're admitting to something. You
don't have to admit to כסף, kessef, you can even admit to
a פרוטה, prutah, okay, even though it's a coin that the תורה
Torah doesn't recognize. If Charlie was here, Charlie would be telling us
that the תורה Torah doesn't recognize any coinage, that coinage only began
after the תורה Torah and the תורה Torah is only talking about
weights of silver. But okay, these are actual, also represent weights, but
that's, you know... These were actual coins, right. Right, anyway, so I
gave you כסף kessef and you said, "No, כי הוא זה," ki
hu zeh, even a פרוטה. prutah. So the question is just going
to be, why do we say two כסף? kessef, Why don't we
just say one? Yeah, you could just say one. Okay, so that's
the גמרא's Gemara question. That's the way רש"י Rashi explains the
question. Okay. התם דומיא דכלים. Hatam dumya d'kelim. No, because it says
כסף או כלים. kesef o kelim. מה כלים שנים אף כסף שנים.
Mah kelim shnayim af kesef shnayim. And once we're going to say
that, we're going to say ומה כסף דבר חשוב אף כלים דבר
חשוב, u'mah kesef davar chashuv af kelim davar chashuv, which is, according
to רש"י, Rashi, a totally parenthetical point, which means it can't even
be like trivial כלים, kelim, it can't be a כלי kli that's
worth like a toothpick or something. It has to have some significant
value. רש"י Rashi says the significant value is that the כלים kelim
themselves have to be worth two כסף, kessef two מעה. meah, But
תוספות Tosafot says that like they just have to be worth a
פרוטה, prutah. they can't be worth less than a פרוטה. prutah. How
can you be less? What? That's right, exactly. Yeah, well, שוה פרוטה.
shaveh prutah. Yeah, well, it's more than, at least worth some value.
It's worth less than a פרוטה. prutah. You could have a כלי
kli less than a פרוטה. prutah, How much do you think one
toothpick costs? Yeah.
One פרוטה. perutah.
No, it costs less than a פרוטה, perutah? I'm promising you that.
Yes, I'm not understanding the מה כלים שנים. mah kelim shnayim.
כלים Kelim is plural.
כלים Kelim is in plural. Yeah, right, exactly. Okay, there we go.
Okay, now the problem still is is that here the גמרא Gemara
seems okay with the idea, all it had to do was double
it. It seems okay with the idea of כסף ממאה kessef m'meah
where although it just says כסף, kessef, but if you look at
the גמרא, Gemara, right, the גמרא, Gemara, you know, it's clear that
that means a מעה, meah. whereas here we're assuming that כסף kessef
got us to דינר, dinar. so it's still not exactly clear why
what but we'll get up to that. All right, so anyway, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this: ורמי מעשר, veramei ma'aser, דכתיב, dechtiv,
וצרת הכסף בידך, v'tzarta hakessef b'yadecha, you bind the money in your
hand when you transfer מעשר ma'aser to money to bring the money
to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, מעשר שני. ma'aser sheni. ותנן, u'tenan, and we have
a משנה, mishnah, הפורט סלע ממעות מעשר. haporet sela m'ma'os ma'aser. If
you are basically, you know, sort of
changing money from מעשר ma'aser money, and the basic case in that
משנה mishnah was, and it sort of discusses how you do it,
but the basic case of the משנה mishnah was that you were
using your copper coins, your פרוטות, perutos, to exchange it for a
larger silver coin, a סלע. sela Okay, which means that you redeemed
your מעשר ma'aser on a פרוטה. perutah How can you redeem your
מעשר ma'aser on a פרוטה? perutah, It says כסף, kessef, and כסף
kessef has to mean the כסף צורי kessef tzuri which starts with
the silver coinage. Okay, so how could you do that? Okay, so
it says,
no, the גמרא Gemara says there, מעשר שני, ma'aser sheni, כסף הכסף
ריבה. kessef hakessef ribah. It says וצרת הכסף, v'tzarta hakessef, it could
have just said וצרת כסף. v'tzarta kessef. So the extra ה hei
is telling you even a broader expanse, any type of coinage, even
not silver. It's funny because the ה hei you would think is
a more limiting word, right? The כסף, kessef, it has to be
real silver. Anyway, so that's how we come to expand and it's
not limited to just silver coinage. ורמי
הקדש, veramei hekdesh, המנא לן, hamana lan, דכתיב, dechtiv, ונתן הכסף וקם
לו, v'natan hakessef v'kam lo, when you redeem something from הקדש, hekdesh,
it says you give the money and it gets and it comes
to you. And again, כסף kessef here we're going to say means
כסף צורי, kessef tzuri, for silver coinage which is right, and so
a פרוטה perutah wouldn't work. והאמר שמואל, v'ha'amar Shmuel, הקדש שוה מנה
שחיללו על שוה פרוטה, hekdesh shaveh maneh shechilelo al shaveh perutah, if
you redeem הקדש hekdesh worth a thousand dollars on a פרוטה, perutah.
מחולל, mechulal, it works. So because even though, you know, you can
understand this in one of two ways, right? You could say yes
it's a purchase and how could it work? You cheated הקדש. hekdesh.
So רש״י Rashi says אין אונאה בהקדש, ein ona'ah b'hekdesh, there's a
special הלכה halacha that the ideas of overcharging don't apply to הקדש,
hekdesh, so בדיעבד, b'diavad, he's not saying it's מותר, mutar, but בדיעבד
b'diavad it works. The other way of understanding this is that הקדש
hekdesh you don't have to see it all as about being a
purchase related, right? That if הקדש hekdesh is about the status that
inheres within the object and you're transferring the status, the question of
value obviously לכתחילה l'chatchilah should be at the same value, but it's
not fundamentally an act of purchase, it's fundamentally an act of being
פודה, podeh, of transferring the status and therefore it works even if
very disparate values. He's not saying you're allowed to, but he's saying
it works. Bottom line though what's relevant for us is that he
says that it works on a פרוטה perutah. even though the תורה
Torah says כסף, kesef right, which should mean that at least we
start at the מעה. So the גמרא Gemara says,
התם, hatam, כסף כסף יליף ממעשר. kessef kessef yalif m'ma'aser. No, since
we already learned from מעשר שני, ma'aser sheni, the הכסף hakessef tells
us even non-silver coinage, the גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah here כסף הכסף,
kessef hakessef, because they're both קדושה kedushah type of ideas, tells us
even non-silver. So we're still insisting that when the תורה Torah talks
about coinage it has to be silver coinage, but now we're finding
a lot of exceptions. Okay, one case it really wasn't an exception,
it was just doubling it. In another case like הקדש hekdesh and
מעשר ma'aser we're allowing even a פרוטה.
perutah, Yeah. Very simple question, maybe it was just answered. You know,
when we learn the שופרות, shofros, when we learn from אם סיסרא,
em Sisra, right, they tell this we learned about a whatever it
is, a שבר, shever, תרועה, teruah, you know, from Sisera, right? We
said oh we also get the hundred קולות kolos from her too,
right? So אברהם Avraham he bought the field for four hundred שקל
כסף עובר לסוחר. shekel kessef over l'socher. And always says the same
thing here. Yeah, well, it's I mean yeah
what can I tell you? There
it's an אסמכתא, asmachta, the hundred קולות kolos are not, you know,
nobody says whatever, that's clearly just a מנהג, minhag, you know. So,
you know, and the עיקר ikar number, I mean there, I mean
your answer is right there, the עיקר ikar number is learned from
the פסוקים psukim themselves about the תקיעות, tekios, right? The rest of
that is just an אסמכתא. asmachta. But I always see the גמרא
Gemara asking.
All right, I hear. I hear.
Fine. I don't know the answer. All right. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this: ורמי קידושי אשה, veramei kiddushei ishah, דכתיב, dechtiv, כי
יקח איש אשה ובעלה,
ki yikach
ish ishah u've'alah, וגמר קיחה קיחה משדה עפרון. vegamar kicha kicha misdeh
Efron. And now we're going to sort of, we're both trying to
understand is this הלכה really true that כסף kesef, means a particular
thing. Okay, but we're also remember, we use this to explain the
position of בית שמאי, Beit Shammai. so that's going to be relevant
as
well. So here yet we're not dealing with בית שמאי. Beit Shammai,
ותנן, u'tenan, בית הלל אומרים בפרוטה ובשוה פרוטה. Beit Hillel omrim b'perutah
u'v'shaveh perutah.
So according to בית הלל, Beit Hillel even though it's based on
כסף, kesef it works with a פרוטה. perutah, So נימא רב אסי
דאמר כבית שמאי? neima Rav Assi d'amar k'Beit Shammai? Is רב אסי
Rav Assi's position a בית שמאי Beis Shammai, position? So it's very
interesting. On עמוד א׳, amud aleph, רב אסי Rav Assi was quoted
to explain בית שמאי. Beis Shammai, But now the גמרא Gemara is
essentially turning it around and saying, I don't get it. You mean
to tell me רב אסי Rav Assi's idea that every time it
says כסף in the תורה Torah means silver is only works within
בית שמאי, Beis Shammai? because בית הלל Beis Hillel says... So it's
very interesting. On עמוד א, Amud Aleph, רב אסי Rav Asi was
quoted to explain בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, but now the גמרא Gemara
is essentially turning it around and saying, "I don't get it. You
mean to tell me רב אסי'ס Rav Asi's idea that every time
it says כסף in the תורה Torah means silver is only works
within בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, because בית הלל says קידושי אשה kiddushei
ishah is a פרוטה, perutah. right? So really, רב אסי Rav Asi
only works for בית שמאי?" Beis Shammai So the גמרא Gemara says,
אלא אי איתמר הכי איתמר. Ela i itmar hachi itmar. Fine, forget
it. We missed, we were explaining רב אסי Rav Asi too broadly.
רב אסי Rav Asi did not mean to say that anytime the
תורה Torah talks about money,
it means silver. And that's why הקדש hekdesh works by פרוטה, perutah!
and קידושי אשה kiddushei ishah works by פרוטה. prutah Money in the
תורה Torah is not limited to silver. So okay, so then what
was רב אסי Rav Asi saying? Here's what he was saying. הכי
אמר, אמר רב יהודה אמר רב אסי, Hachi amar, amar Rav Yehudah
amar Rav Asi, כל כסף קצוב האמור בתורה כסף צורי. Kol kesef
katzuv ha-amur ba-Torah kesef Tzuri. When the תורה Torah doesn't just talk
generically about money, when it gives a precise amount, right? If it
just says you should redeem it on money, right? You know, so
money means any money. I'm not telling you what money. You want
to use a copper coin? Go to it! Use a פרוטה! prutah
But when it gives you an amount, we have to know what
coin we're talking about. So when the תורה Torah just talks about
money generically, any money. But when the תורה Torah talks about an
amount, then we're talking about כסף צורי, kesef Tzuri, okay, which is
silver and a particular high-valued
currency. כל כסף קצוב, Kol kesef katzuv, we're going to get back
to that, האמור בתורה כסף צורי ha-amur ba-Torah kesef Tzuri ושל דבריהם
veshel divreihem, כסף מדינה. kesef Medina מאי קמשמע לן? Mai kamashma lan?
So now how is that telling us something new? תנינא, Tanina, we've
already taught it. חמישה סלעים של בן, Chamishah sela'im shel ben, the
five סלע sela of the son, right, the סלע sela. here is
the שקל, shekel the five שקל shekel in the תורה Torah for
פדיון
הבן, pidyon haben, שלשים של עבד, sheloshim shel eved, the thirty שקל
for a slave who's gored, right, וחמישים של אונס ושל מפתה, ve-chamishim
shel ones veshel mefateh, and the fifty of the מוהר בתולות moher
betulot for the case of rape and seduction, מאה שמוציא שם, me'ah
shemotzi shem, and the hundred of the guy who slanders his wife,
כולם בשקל הקדש, kulam be-shekel hakodesh, all of them are in the
שקל הקדש, shekel hakodesh, במנה צורי, be-maneh Tzuri, and that is the
שקל that we know of in the צורי Tzuri type of coinage.
So
רב אסי, Rav Asi, the fact that every fixed amount in the
תורה Torah is כסף צורי, kesef Tzuri, it's in a משנה. Mishnah.
So it says, no, his חידוש chiddush was the second part. ושל
דבריהם כסף מדינה אצטריכא ליה דלא תנא. Veshel divreihem kesef medinah itztericha
lei de-lo tana. That was his חידוש. chiddush. When we speak about
rabbinic coinage, a rabbinic obligation, he wanted to tell us that you
have to understand that that is a different coinage; that is כסף
מדינה. kesef medinah. דתניא, Detanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Baraita, התוקע
לחבירו, ha-toke'a le-chavero, somebody like, you know, hit somebody in the ear,
okay, it's particularly like in the ear, נותן לו סלע. notein lo
sela. He gives him a סלע. sela Now, a סלע sela we
would say would be down here, right? If you—that, but רב אסי
Rav Asi is telling us, no, no, no, that's כסף צורי. kesef
Tzuri. Anything that's in—that's a rabbinic obligation that's a fixed amount is
talking—and uses a—and uses a coin reference to a type of a
coinage, it's talking about כסף מדינה kesef medinah which is only one-eighth
of the value. So what's going to be one-eighth of the value
of this? So one-quarter of the value will be a דינר, dinar,
right? Four דינר dinar, to whatever. So this is going to be
a half of this, a half of a זוז, zuz, which is
this איסתירא. istira.
Okay, so let's take a look on
your—what—how come מנה maneh is not on the list? That's—is that not
a coinage?
A מנה maneh is a hundred זוז.
zuz, Yeah,
hundred זוז, zuz. a hundred דינר.
dinar. Yeah, hundred דינר, dinar. yeah. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says, דתניא התוקע לחבירו נותן לו סלע. Detanya ha-toke'a le-chavero notein lo
sela. ולא תימא מאי סלע ארבעה זוזי, Ve-lo teima mai sela arba'ah
zuzay, don't say a סלע sela. is here, which is four זוז,
zuz okay,
that סלע. sela. אלא מאי סלע פלגא דזוזי, Ela mai sela palga
de-zuzay, it's an eighth of this, so it's a half—so this would
be a quarter, it would be a half of a
זוז. zuz דאבדי אינשי תרתי לפלגא דזוזי איסתירא, De-avdi inshei tarti le-palga
de-zuzay istira, and people call a half of a זוז zuz. an
איסתירא. istira. See, I had it up here already. An איסתירא, istira,
apparently the reason it's referring to this name is somehow איסתירא istira
is a similar word to the name of סלע. sela I don't
know. But that's what it's saying. It's saying the סלע sela when
we're talking about a סלע מדינה, sela medinah, that's איסתירא, istira, okay,
which is a word for סלע sela, but it's a word for
the local סלע, which is one-eighth. Okay. So that's anyway—so that's what
he's telling you. He's telling you that when there's coin—a specific amount,
if it's in the תורה, Torah, it's the bigger coinage. If it's
in the—if it's a rabbinic obligation, then the words that we're using
really refer to one-eighth of the value. Which, as I said, the
big נפקא מינא is what is the two hundred זוז zuz of
a כתובה. kesuvah Okay, if you say כתובה דאורייתא, kesuvah d'Oraisa, it's
two hundred of these זוז. zuz But if you say it's דרבנן,
d'Rabbanan, we'll say the word זוז zuz. refers to a זוז zuz.
of an eighth of the value. And actually, according to those that
פוסקן pasken that a כתובה was a דרבנן, d'Rabbanan, they actually said
that it was only twenty-five of these זוז. It was two hundred—that's
an eighth, right?—it was two hundred of the cheaper זוז. Okay, so
this is the question: if something is a biblical obligation, we're talking
about
these values; if something is rabbinic, you take something here and you
divide it by eight. Okay, so it's a big נפקא מינא. Anyway,
now what we've done, though, is is we've put aside this idea
to explain בית שמאי, because we've... Okay, that it says, it says
כסף, but it says it generically in the תורה. Torah. So it
doesn't explain why בית שמאי, why a פרוטה prutah, wouldn't be enough
if it just says כסף generically, a פרוטה prutah. should really be
enough. Is it? Oh, we have two minutes. Okay. So let's just
read one more answer. רבי שמעון בן לקיש, Rebbi Shimon ben Lakish,
so you're right, we can't use that to explain בית שמאי anymore.
So רבי שמעון בן לקיש Rebbi Shimon ben Lakish אמר טעמא דבית
שמאי כדחזקיה, amar tama d'Beis Shammai k'd'Chizkiya, like חזקיה, Chizkiya, דאמר חזקיה
אמר קרא
והפדה. d'amar Chizkiya amar kra v'hofdah. This is by the אמה עבריה,
amah ivriyah, that the man sold his daughter as a slave and
she could be redeemed. And of course this is going to be
a model: selling your daughter as a slave and selling your daughter
as a wife. So מלמד שמגרעת מפדיונה ויוצאה. melamed she'migra'at mipidyona v'yotza.
So the fact from והפדה v'hofdah we learn that the slave can
buy back his or her own freedom. You bought me for X
amount, I've worked X number of years, we'll sort of, we'll pro-rate
it and you could buy it back based on the amount that's
left over. So how much was this girl bought for as a
slave? אי אמרת בשלמא דיהב לה דינר, ee amart bishlama d'yhav la
dinar, if she was bought for a substantial amount like a
דינר, dinar. היינו דמגרעה ואזלה, hayno d'migrava v'azla, that's how you can
discount it based on the amount that's been worked, because there was
a whole דינר. dinar, So now, okay, you worked half, so you
have to only pay half and you keep on cutting,
working your way down until whatever is left of that original purchase
price, and that's what you pay. אלא אי אמרת דיהב לה פרוטה,
ela ee amart d'yhav la prutah, but if she was only bought
for a פרוטה, prutah. so מפרוטה מי מגרעה, miprutah mi migrava, you
can't go less than a פרוטה. prutah, So since we see that
when the girl is sold as a slave, the idea is that
she could be, you'd be reducing the amount, you see that she's
being sold for more than a פרוטה. prutah Now, of course, just
because it's more than a פרוטה, prutah, there's a whole range of
coinage between a פרוטה and a דינר. It doesn't explain how we're
going to presume a דינר. Okay, but the argument is going to
be, and we'll pick up with this tomorrow, that once she's being
sold for more than a פרוטה, we're going to assume it's something
significant, a דינר, and once we're going to assume that that's how
the girl is sold as a slave, then we're going to assume
that that's also the model for קידושין. Once again, this whole selling
and slavery of the model for קידושין, okay, so we'll pick up
with that tomorrow.